And this video we learn about rotations at the time of insertion that is at the time of creation of
a year.
When we are creating an avian tree and inserting any key into a reality then some laws may become imbalance.
So tree becomes imbalance.
So go balance that we performed our patients so those rotations are named as another rotation out of
rotation a lot and all of our patients will understand all this for patients one by one.
So let us start with the first one.
First one a little rotation little logistic of initial three.
Suppose this was the initial avian tree.
What are the balance factors.
See this balance factor of this zero.
And this is one and zero.
So this is one minus zero is one for balance factor of the smallest one.
Then I want to insert the value ten so after inserting 10 in this one for 10 will come then it's less
than 30 less then print so it will come on the side.
So Turkey green tea and then what are the balance factors.
This is zero.
This is one minus zero so one.
This is it two minus zero on this site.
So this is two.
So this new order became imbalance of the balance Factor Four should not be more than one.
So what the balance factor is two.
So this order became imbalance.
No we're going to give the name for the imbalance when this node became imbalance because of insertion
of.
So in direction Dr. Tennyson so that left off left.
So I will give the name as an imbalance.
So this is a really matter for a little imbalance.
How the perform rotation.
Let us take the tree once again here.
Still perform rotation around this node still perform a rotation in the static direction.
So what does it mean by rotation.
Imagine that this is a trader.
Okay keep your finger here and pull the thread on this site pull the thread on this side.
So if you pull the thread it will rotate around the finger right so then it rotate around the Finger
Turkey will come on this site and printing will move up at here and then will move a little above its
position.
So the tree looks like this.
That's the meaning of rotation.
Hold your finger and move this node so rotate around your finger rotate around a fixed point okay.
So this the rotated 3.
Let us check the balance factors.
This is 0.
This is one minus 1 0.
A lot of balance are on which an order we have rotated this node so at that place who is there not 20.
Is it balance or not.
Yes it became yes.
But in fact it became zero.
So on whichever known you perform rotation the balance factor should become zero for X1 earlier objective
position the balance factor was 2 not the same position the benefactor is 0.
So this is the procedure for rotation not for the important things.
First team what should be the name of this rotation imbalance.
I explain a little imbalance right.
So let us call the rotation also a little station so I'll give them the mass and then rotation.
So based on imbalance I have given the rotation name once was eleven now you can say that no no it is
rotating on the right hand side we are pulling it on the right hand side.
Call it has a right rotation OK.
That is also correct.
Then somebody say that.
No no it is rotating like a clock.
So it is clockwise rotation.
OK call it does clockwise clockwise rotation so you can give any name that is no standard name for this
one right.
This is a subtle patient.
There is no standard name.
So if you want you can give any name I have selected the names so that it is easy for understanding
even the complex things.
So I'm calling does a Latin mass if I call it as right rotation or a clockwise rotation maybe I may
not be able to explain you that things more clearly that is follow a little rotation.
So this is after an end rotation.
So this is about name.
Second thing second important thing you hear me thinking that I have taken just a small degree just
with the three notes what I should do if the tree is very big so don't worry.
Rotations are always done with the three notes on me always so delicately notes even if a tree is having
toes and nodes also rotations perform over three notes for me.
So understand this clearly then two examples.
I will show you how this is done on bigger sites that results.
So that's all about force rotation right now.
Next we will look at r r or patient for all our rotation.
This the initial three balance factor leaves no to zero and this one is zero minus one.
So this is minus.
Next I will insert 13 this one so can I'm pretty are already there.
So 30 is greater than 10 and greater than pretty sweet comes from this not a balanced factor of this
one zero this is zero minus one minus one this is zero minus two.
So this is minus two minus two is not a valid balance factor but fact cannot be less than minus one.
This is minus 2.
So this nor to begin imbalance.
So why did it became imbalanced.
Because we have inserted Tati just now very we have inserted a right Chertoff right chain right.
It is a right cello right.
And so on.
So let us call decides r r imbalance.
Now let us see how to perform rotation.
So I agree.
I'll take a dream once again perform rotation around this mood in this indentation third means hold
your finger here and pull this turn on the side.
So if you pull it down on this side then 10 comes here.
Burundi will take the place of 10 and 20 will move up a little bit.
Now the balance factor of this is 0.
This is 0 and this is also equal.
So it's perfectly balanced.
Now what should be the name of this rotation.
As I said this is r imbalance so let us call the size on our rotation only.
So this is r vacation.
So this is after R R rotation.
If you say no no this is less protection.
Okay you call it if you said no no this is counter-clockwise rotation.
Okay you can call it you can give any name you like that song.
One important thing in a little rotation the final result was this one previous rotation and this audition
also same result.
Yes in all four rotation that did just a three N V get the same result.
That is a balance.
Now next rotation will look at that is a lot for a lot of attention.
This is the initial treat.
Let us insert Brenda in this one so all right.
No.
Three's having tardy and can do indeed is less than 30 so it will come one less site but it is greater
than 10 so it will come on right side.
One of the balance factors this is zero this is zero minus one minus one.
This is one two minus the two.
So this is to do minus single.
This note became imbalance.
This is imbalance vision direction in session is a done just not being sort of 20 on which side.
Left right so left right first left child and right.
Che l r imbalance.
So let us call the size L R imbalance and hold orientation should we perform.
I will read all three here.
So forcible perform rotation around the snored like this.
So what then with the reserved thirty brandy and then right or ten holding a finger here or it and then
come the side Brandy moves up.
So this holiday tree looks like the balance factors of 0 1 and 2 not perform rotation around this morgue
like this what is the result.
Same order.
So trendy in the root 10 and 30 see put out on the side.
So Brandy will move up today will come down and turn also will move up the balance factor side 0 0 0.
What do you got to do this.
OK rotation and occupation.
This is also an art if you want to give the name based on the direction of rotation.
Just watch it left rotation then the right rotation so this is a lot only with that perspective also
it does so this is a lot rotation.
See this is one rotation only but there are two steps in this one so we call this has double the rotation
we call it gets a double rotation like that I will talk about this one this looks a little complex how
to do this so I show your direct method for this one let us take this stream once again here.
So this time should move this site route should move this site and this newly inserted move should go
in the place of route so Trinity will slip on this site right.
It will come on this site Turkey will move towards right Grandi when it went on the route pretty went
on right but instead of two steps we can see it as a single step.
So we have to send this nor there and move that northern on site for that solar water lock then order.
I will explain you quickly you have understood how these are working for our location.
This is the initial tree 10 in Turkey.
Right now we will insert a new element trained in this one.
So if we insert Brandy Brandy is greater than 10 but less than 30.
So he'd come to this site then the balance factors are 0 1 and this is minus 2.
So this became imbalance which imbalance right left.
So are El imbalance so in sharp eyed or orderly imbalance and loading sea we get that rather other.
So that's why I did not remove it.
We get that a on the always we are getting similar there for three knots.
Anyway you have to perform rotation on this one.
So I take a treat once again but in fact inside zero 1 and minus two perform rotation performed a rotation
with this node first so then that displays comes 20 and on the right side it will be Turkey for the
balance factor side of zero minus 1 and minus 2 then perform rotation around this more this more we
get that present tense pull the down 20 comes here today also more so we get that if you want to see
your direct method then this should be sent as a rule or a parent and this should move one left side.
So again this is also double the rotation right because there are two steps.
Actually these are the steps but for understanding we take that one so whichever you are comfortable
with you can follow that one.
That's all about four rotations we saw let me write on the rotations.
We have seen first as a little rotation the eleventh hour out on probation.
These are called us single rotations.
These were having single step and a lot an all of Ghana's double rubbish.
But don't count desires.
Rotations count as one only.
See there is a difference between a double and two.
So don't count the mass to rotation.
This rotation if I take a lot less one rotation but it is having both steps so it is double capacities
double sizes double number of steps.
Steps are double by so this one on me but his size is double.
So that's all about rotations now out of four rotations.
I'll give you one observation that may be very useful for you.
That would be logical useful for you observe this one so all the four rotations.
What does the observation look at here.
So using three keys or three laws.
So I have a three notes that is the three keys using three keys how many different binary search fields
we can form five how to N C and men plus one number of binary search streets we can create out of n
keys so far 3 5 3s we can create.
So what are those how they look like.
I will draw them.
See these other five trees out of three keys.
We can generate five different binary search trees to NC and man plus 1 5 our possible what is the height.
0 1 2 0 1 2 0 1 0 1 2 0 1 0.
That is of minimum height so for trees of larger height and that is of smaller height AVR trees means
height.
Balance binary search tree so which is more height.
Balance.
So when you have three keys you can draw binary search free of any shape or a lot of binary so she's
only so if you have this one why don't you take that one change this one to that one horrible change
we are saying that we are performing rotation we are saying that we are performing rotation or this
one or this one are double the rotation right first on this one.
Next on this one or double the rotation Foster on this one then on this one.
So actually we have transformed these four trees and Kodak tree because that is height of balance and
how we transform.
We are seeing that we have performed rotation so this is the idea behind a trees so idea originates
from here.
Then you can have five different shapes.
Why don't you select that ship even if you've got this one modify it even if you got this one modified
it to that ship.
So this all about rotations at the time of creation at the time of insertion.
Next we will see the examples.
If a tree is bigger Howard or patient is perform I'll discuss various things in that topic.