Yeah.
The topic is height versus Nord analysis for aviary trees.
Similar analysis we have already done for general binary trees and strict binary trees and also for
complete or strict energy trees.
We have done the same analysis.
I will do that analysis upon.
So what do we have to do is if height of our aviary is given height as a given then fine minimum how
many ones are possible in that kite man Zimmerman how many lawns are possible in that pipe so a military
is a binary tree only basically by military then by Navy SEALs street then it is height to balance of
binary search for basically it is a binary tree.
So in any binary tree if height for tree is given then maximum how many nodes can we do to bind each
plus one minus one N will be dead.
Yes we know this one.
So I don't have to explain that one.
So this is coming from binary trees right.
So anyway I will come across this formula once again.
Now the question is minimum how many n if height is given.
So how to get the formula C formula by taking the sample values are examples from the observation you
can prepare the formula so formulas come from observation.
Let us take some examples of some heights of a few trees then see how many minimum notes required.
Then we'll come up with the formula.
So let me show you some examples.
First example let us assume that high.
This one.
What about height.
Zero level stock height from 1 onwards right.
So here we will start from the same height as 1.
Then just one Lord I'm not labelling I'm not putting any values.
So how many loans required minimum one only maximum also one minimum one for one high does not zero
height is starting for one the next.
If height is two then minimum how many laws are required.
Do not see as I do not if high desert 3 then the minimum how many n Reynolds 3 Norfolk y minimum 3 n
no wrong.
This is wrong.
Is it a military aviator agreements height balance safety check the balance factors this is zero.
This is one and this is a two.
This is not balance so I need one more Lord on this side to make it balance.
Yes not a balance factor Assad 0 0 1 0 and this is one yes.
This is the balance that set minimum Nordmann.
It must be balance.
So minimum.
How many notes required for notes required.
So take four then then to hide this for and then at minimum how many notes required.
One two three four is in balance.
No this site I need some n one nor is it sufficient.
No still it is in balance one more nor is it balance.
No yes that is valid.
What about this note.
This is not balanced.
How.
Now everything is balance.
Let us check.
0 1 0.
And this is one this is zero.
This is minus one.
And this is one.
One two three one two.
Yes.
So total how many in order to the flag.
One two three four five six seven seven Nordic flag mainly among seven North required for height four
where the heights are starting from 1 onwards.
That 4 5 also I draw I right here.
There is no space on that site.
If height is a 5 then the minimum.
How many noughts required.
I not right.
One two three four five.
No there's not balance.
If you have five no deciding during this one for normal with there then only this balance.
Okay one two three.
Total one two three four.
Yes perfect.
Including that group.
Then what about this for this including this one one two three four you have.
So you should have one.
One two three.
No it is balance.
Now here you have three.
So here you should have to balance.
Here you have three.
Here you should have to balance.
No this is a balance.
If you check the balance factor for all the lords then the tree is a balance.
But how many nodes are there.
One two three four five six seven eight nine ten eleven two one.
So minimum two will static land.
Yes.
Now we have enough examples for observation and to get the farm along.
No I have some set of values.
Let me pick a better table if height is given then how many loads for a given height.
Let us make it our function so if height is 1 1 Node 2 2 3 4 2 2 3 4 4 7 4 7 5 2 1 5 2 then I'll extend
it 6 and 7.
Tell me the answer for this.
I got this too.
Let us observe 4 plus 7 eleven eleven plus one okay.
Four plus seven plus one.
Am I getting this value also like that only two plus four six plus one.
Yes seven.
How I got this one.
One plus two three plus one four.
So it means this one is seven plus two L 19 plus one twenty then how to get this one twenty plus twenty
thirty two plus one thirty three yes.
So the formalise number also laws for a given height as previous two values are either then plus 1.
So and off at minus two plus and of two minus one plus one plus one yes this is the formula then for
the very first value I should have two values with me so then height is a zero answer is zero then hide
this one then the answer is one right.
Otherwise this is done.
So in height to zero onset of zero height if one answer is one otherwise this is the formula used for
formula for a minimum is this one and for this this the table so minimum n can be obtained by this formula
so I should write on this formula here for a minimum N0 I would not write the formula I will say look
in the table so far a minimum launch to look into the table so if I guessed minimum go alongside a six
minimum print in order like this then there is one change here see I started height from 1 onwards then
I have only one note height this one onward so if height is a three then seven n seven notes right this
height is three 1 2 3 so maximum 7 N1 the height is a 3 so this maximum known formula we will get it
to board that ship plus one minus one but no we will have just to put H minus one formula because the
height is a starting from 1 onwards for maximum nought formalized this fund so if I add this one more
and these are two N and these are one two three four more so to square so this is one plus two plus
two square is equals to two cube minus 1 to cube minus 1 is what h minus 1 that is 7.
So yes we have a 7 or so this is 2 cube height is 3.
So just to polish minus one Now we have the formulas if height is given that the minimum north and maximum
n we need another formula if no exotic given that modest minimum height and maximum height so let me
I don't know if remove this if and nodes are given then find minimum height and maximum height so if
you remember in binary trees what we did is we converted this minimum form a la to maximum formula and
maximum form a local minimum formula will do the same thing here so we don't have to do any analysis
see maximum laws are any equal to two bodies plus one minus one then minimum height will be edge is
equals to endless one log base 2 so log B is to endless morning of minus 1 because in power we don't
have plus one here.
So log based wind plus 1 then what about maximum height.
This comes from minimum North formula.
There it is look under tables so here also look in the table you have to look into the table how.
Let me give an example.
If I have a tool n then what is the maximum height size.
If I have putting n tardiness less than being D so beside only here only putting n also 5 15 n 5 only
maximum height maximum height 5 19 n height is 5 maximum so these are minimum notes required for getting
this height.
Now I have 20 n okay maximum height of 6 maximum height defects.
So from this to well go 19 maximum height is five.
Bring T2 today to maximum height to six so you can look into the table and you can read this letter
and stuff and stuff from height towards Lord.
You have to see from note towards height that set so you can find out.
So you have to practice this little bit put it by yourself using pen and paper then you will remember
everything right.
Just practice it once you will remember it.
So we have done in-depth analysis of a reality.
Now one lasting see this formula for a minimum number of nodes of farm like this one minimum number
of four nodes formula.
Actually this formula is meant for this one and also useful here.
Pi does given n minimum n formula.
This formalized same as Fibonacci series formula.
Yes Fibonacci series is famous for being a balanced series balanced series.
You pick any good arms off you will CCD like high and as a plus one any build done for example effort
10 and F eleven two thumbs then f 11 by effort.
Then if you do R F I plus one by F I.
If you do a ratio will be one point six approximately.
Not exactly.
It may be 1 1 5 9 8 baby one point 5 7 also you should accept that as one point six or it may 1 point
6 1 6 2 also approximately one point 6.
So any two consecutive numbers if you take the ratio at is one point six so Fibonacci series is believed
to be are balanced series.
So this formalize a matching with Fibonacci series means aviary trees are also balanced does it prove
that they are balance because so therefore allow for more towards us height same as Fibonacci series
then one last time minimum hide is log in plus one base to maximum height look into the table table
is from the formula.
So from this formula contact calculate height.
Yes approximately if you calculate from this one there is a derivation if we derive that and get done
so then approximately approximately it is equal to one point forty four log base 2 and plus 2 if you
use this form land converted in dozens of log in we get the funds so minimum height is also logarithmic
maximum height is also multiple of logarithmic but logarithmic so aviary tree's height as always in
terms of the log that.
This is enough with the analysis of hi towards us notes.